Guide to the Albert Galloway Keller Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1894-1952; Series II; 9.25 linear feet (26 boxes)
  - Published Books
    - Science of Society
      - Draft of Part V, AMs
        - Chapter LIV (Box 22, Folder 694)
        - Chapter LV (Box 22, Folder 695)
      - Proofsheets of Part V, Chapter LV, Sections 414-416 (Box 22, Folder 696)
      - Draft of Part V, AMs
        - Chapter LVI (Box 22, Folder 697)
        - Chapter LVII (Box 22, Folder 698)
      - Draft of Part VI, AMs
        - Chapter LIX (Box 22, Folder 699)
        - Chapter LX (Box 22, Folder 700)
      - Outline for Volume IV - Casebook, AMs (Box 22, Folder 701)
      - Mental Outfit, AMs
        - pp. 1-50 (Box 22, Folder 702)
        - pp. 51-100 (Box 22, Folder 703)
        - pp. 101-200 (Box 22, Folder 704)
        - pp. 201-300 (Box 22, Folder 705)
        - pp. 301-400 (Box 22, Folder 706)
        - pp. 401-500 (Box 22, Folder 707)
        - pp. 501-600 (Box 23, Folder 708)
        - pp. 601-700 (Box 23, Folder 709)
        - pp. 701-800 (Box 23, Folder 710)
        - pp. 801-825 (Box 23, Folder 711)
        - Unidentified fragments (Box 23, Folder 712)
      - Scattered pages of an early draft, AMs (Box 23, Folder 713)
      - Scattered pages from early drafts, TMs, undated (Box 23, Folder 714)
      - Comments on various portions of the unfinished book, TMs (Box 23, Folder 715)
      - Comments on various portions of the unfinished book, AMs (Box 23, Folder 716-717)
      - Comments on various portions of the unfinished book, TMs (Box 23, Folder 718)
      - Comments on the draft (Box 23, Folder 719)
      - Note on joint authorship (Box 23, Folder 720)
      - Reviews and advertisements, 1927 (Box 23, Folder 721)
        See also: box 2, folder 38 See also: box 2, folder 57 See also: box 3, folder 85-87 See also: box 3, folder 100-101 See also: box 10, folder 400-421 See also: box 9, folder 322 See also: box 4, folder 105 See also: box 13, folder 523 See also: box 13, folder 525 See also: box 14, folder 573-576 See also: box 50, folder 1317-1343
    - Man's Rough Road, 1932
      See also: box 2, folder 58 box 3, folder 89 box 3, folder 101 box 4, folder 109-110 box 11, folder 420-432 box 14, folder 577-578 box 50, folder 1341-1358
      - "Foreword", TMs (Box 23, Folder 722)
      - Draft, AMs
        - Chapters 1-4 (Box 23, Folder 723)
        - Chapters 5-8 (Box 23, Folder 724)
        - Chapters 9-12 (Box 23, Folder 725)
        - Chapters 13-16 (Box 23, Folder 726)
        - Chapters 17-20 (Box 23, Folder 727)
        - Chapters 21-24 (Box 23, Folder 728)
      - Proofsheets (Box 24, Folder 729)
      - Book reviews (Box 24, Folder 730)
        See also: box 2, folder 58 See also: box 3, folder 89 See also: box 3, folder 101 See also: box 4, folder 109-110 See also: box 11, folder 420-432 See also: box 14, folder 577-578 See also: box 50, folder 1341-1358
    - Reminiscences of William Graham Sumner, 1933
      - Revised draft, TMs (Box 24, Folder 731)
      - TMs (Box 24, Folder 732)
      - Book reviews (Box 24, Folder 733)
    - Brass Tacks, 1938
      - pp. 1-96, AMs (Box 25, Folder 734)
      - pp. 97-215, AMs (Box 25, Folder 735)
      - Proofsheets (Box 25, Folder 736)
        See also: box 9, folder 314 See also: box 9, folder 331-334 See also: box 4, folder 135
    - Net Impressions, 1942
      - TMs
        - Chapter III (Box 25, Folder 737)
        - Chapter V (Box 25, Folder 738)
        - Chapter XI (Box 25, Folder 739)
        - Chapter XII (Box 25, Folder 740)
        - Chapter XIII (Box 25, Folder 741)
        - Book reviews (Box 25, Folder 742)
  - Unpublished Books
    - "Twilight of Common Sense", 1935
      - Original essay (Box 25, Folder 743)
      - Drafts of prefaces (Box 25, Folder 744)
      - First draft, AMs
        - pp. 1-24 (Box 25, Folder 745)
        - pp. 148-200 (Box 25, Folder 746)
        - pp. 201-250 (Box 25, Folder 747)
        - pp. 251-300 (Box 25, Folder 748)
      - Second draft, TMs
        - pp. 53-77 (Box 25, Folder 749)
        - pp. 78-159 (Box 25, Folder 750)
        - pp. 162-227 (Box 25, Folder 751)
      - Final draft, TMs
        - pp. 1-101 (Box 25, Folder 752)
        - pp. 102-209 (Box 26, Folder 753)
        - pp. 222-245 (Box 26, Folder 754)
          See also: box 7, folder 228 See also: box 13, folder 489 See also: box 13, folder 496
    - "Elementary Sociology", 1942
      - AMs
        - pp. 1-100 (Box 26, Folder 755)
        - pp. 101-200 (Box 26, Folder 756)
        - pp. 201-281 (Box 26, Folder 757)
      - TMs
        - pp. 1-64 (Box 26, Folder 758)
        - pp. 65-205 (Box 26, Folder 759)
        - pp. 206-285 (Box 26, Folder 760)
        - pp. 1-64, 103-104, 114 (Box 26, Folder 761)
        - pp. 127-205 (Box 26, Folder 762)
        - pp. 206-253 (Box 26, Folder 763)
          See also: box 2, folder 45
    - "Clarence Day: The Journeyman Years", 1949
      - Typescript sent to Knopf (Box 26, Folder 764)
      - First typed draft, TMs (Box 26, Folder 765)
      - Second typed draft, TMs (Box 27, Folder 766)
      - Photographs of Day's letters and drawings (Box 27, Folder 767-768)
      - Discarded material, AMs and TMs (Box 27, Folder 769)
      - Additions (Box 27, Folder 770)
      - First draft, AMs (Box 28, Folder 771)
      - Second typed draft: revised, TMs (Box 28, Folder 772)
      - Final draft: incomplete, TMs (Box 28, Folder 773)
        See also: box 9, folder 314-318 See also: box 2, folder 59-97 See also: box 4, folder 103 See also: box 4, folder 104 See also: box 10, folder 379-389
    - "Word Genealogy and Survivals", 1950
      - Early draft, AMs
        - Chapters I-II (Box 28, Folder 774)
        - Chapter III (Box 28, Folder 775)
        - Chapters I-IV, pp. 1-108 (Box 28, Folder 776)
        - Chapter IV, pp. 109-171 (Box 28, Folder 777)
        - Chapter V, pp. 286-345 (Box 28, Folder 779)
      - Keller's notes used in the preparation, AMs (Box 28, Folder 780)
      - Discarded material, AMs (Box 28, Folder 781)
      - TMs
        - Chapters I-III (Box 28, Folder 782)
        - Chapters I-IV, pp. 1-108 (Box 29, Folder 783)
        - Chapter IV, pp. 109-197 (Box 29, Folder 784)
        - Chapter V (Box 29, Folder 785)
        - Chapter I-III (Box 29, Folder 786)
        - Chapter I-IV, pp 1-108 (Box 29, Folder 787)
        - Chapter IV, pp. 109-197 (Box 29, Folder 788)
        - Fragment from Chapter IV (Box 29, Folder 789)
        - Chapter V (Box 29, Folder 790)
          See also: box 8, folder 290-293 See also: box 15, folder 589
    - "Pedagography", 1952
      - First draft, AMs
        - Preface (Box 30, Folder 791)
        - pp. 1-100 (Box 30, Folder 792)
        - pp. 101-200 (Box 30, Folder 793)
        - pp. 201-300 (Box 30, Folder 794)
        - pp. 301-400 (Box 30, Folder 795)
        - unspecified (Box 30, Folder 796)
      - TMs
        - Parts I-VI (Box 31, Folder 797)
        - Parts VII-X (Box 31, Folder 798)
        - Parts XI-XIV (Box 31, Folder 799)
        - Part XV (Box 31, Folder 800)
  - Fiction
    - Play: "The Exquisite", 1928 (Box 32, Folder 800)
      - AMs (Box 32, Folder 801-802)
    - Play: "The Ithakans", 1928
      - Early draft, AMs (Box 32, Folder 803)
      - Early draft, TMs (Box 32, Folder 804)
      - With heavy revisions (Box 32, Folder 805)
      - TMs, 1930 (Box 32, Folder 806-807)
      - With editorial comments, TMs (Box 32, Folder 808)
      - Final draft, TMs (Box 32, Folder 809)
      - Editorial comments, TMs, 1930 (Box 32, Folder 810)
        See also: box 2, folder 53 See also: box 2, folder 58
    - Play: "Odysseus Return", AMs, 1939 (Box 32, Folder 811)
    - "The Disstons"
      - TMs
        - pp. 1-166 (Box 32, Folder 812)
        - pp. 167-319 (Box 32, Folder 813)
        - pp. 1-166 (Box 32, Folder 814)
        - pp. 167-319 (Box 32, Folder 815)
      - AMs
        - pp. 1-145 (Box 32, Folder 816)
        - pp. 146-280 (Box 33, Folder 817)
        - pp. 281-421 (Box 33, Folder 818)
    - "The Father of the Man"
      - AMs
        - pp. 1-100 (Box 33, Folder 819)
        - pp. 101-200 (Box 33, Folder 820)
        - pp. 201-300 (Box 33, Folder 821)
        - pp. 301-400 (Box 33, Folder 822)
        - pp. 401-500 (Box 33, Folder 823)
        - pp. 501-580 (Box 33, Folder 824)
      - Second draft, AMs
        - pp. 314-413 (Box 33, Folder 825)
        - pp. 414-519 (Box 33, Folder 826)
      - Discarded material, AMs (Box 33, Folder 827)
      - TMs
        - pp. 1-100 (Box 33, Folder 828)
        - pp. 101-200 (Box 33, Folder 829)
        - pp. 201-259 (Box 34, Folder 830)
        - pp. 1-100 (Box 34, Folder 831)
        - pp. 101-200 (Box 34, Folder 832)
        - pp. 201-258 (Box 34, Folder 833)
      - Draft, AMs
        - pp. 1-100 (Box 34, Folder 834)
        - pp. 101-210 (Box 34, Folder 835)
      - TMs (Box 34, Folder 836)
        See also: box 2, folder 68
    - "The Hardshell"
      - AMs
        - pp. 1-100 (Box 34, Folder 837)
        - pp. 101-200 (Box 34, Folder 838)
        - pp. 201-300 (Box 34, Folder 839)
        - pp. 301-368 (Box 34, Folder 840)
      - Discarded material, AMs (Box 34, Folder 841)
      - TMs
        - pp. 1-137 (Box 34, Folder 842)
        - pp. 138-248 (Box 34a, Folder 843)
        - pp. 1-137 (Box 34a, Folder 844)
        - pp. 138-248 (Box 34a, Folder 845)
    - Poem: Alkestis, TMs (Box 34a, Folder 846)
      See also: box 3, folder 72
    - Two untitled poems, AMs and TMs (Box 34a, Folder 847)
  - Essays, Lectures and Notebooks
    - Essay: "On Money," Ams, 1894-1895 (Box 35, Folder 848)
    - Notebook: Anthropology, 1895-1896 (Box 35, Folder 849)
    - Notebook: History of Modern Europe, 1895-1896 (Box 35, Folder 850)
    - Notebook: Science of Society, 1895-1896 (Box 35, Folder 851)
    - Notebook: Societology, 1896-1897 (Box 35, Folder 852-853)
    - Unidentified (Box 35, Folder 854)
    - Essay: "Medeavalism in Universities", Ams, 1897 (Box 35, Folder 855)
    - Book review of Alfr. Lehmann's Overtoog Trolddom, printed, 1900 April (Box 35, Folder 856)
    - Letter to the editor of The Evening Post, printed, 1903 January 30 (Box 35, Folder 857)
    - Essay: "A Sociological View of the 'Native Question'", printed, 1903 November (Box 35, Folder 858)
    - Essay: "The Theory of Descent and the Social Sciences", printed, 1904 February (Box 35, Folder 859)
    - Essay: "The Teaching of Commercial Geography", printed, 1907 January (Box 35, Folder 860)
    - Essay: "Controlling Conditions of Commerce", printed, 1908 March (Box 35, Folder 861)
    - Essay: "The Study of Homeric Religion", printed, 1910 March (Box 35, Folder 862)
    - Essay: "William Graham Sumner, The Idealist", 1910 May (Box 35, Folder 863)
    - Essay: Introduction to War and Other Essays, TMs, 1911 April 25 (Box 35, Folder 864)
    - Letter to the editor of The Evening Post, printed, 1913 February 3 (Box 35, Folder 865)
    - Letter to the editor of the Nation, 1914 (Box 35, Folder 866)
    - Letter to the editor of the The Forum, 1915 December 23 (Box 35, Folder 867)
    - Essay: "Sociology and Science", TMs, 1916 May 8 (Box 35, Folder 868)
    - Essay: "Sociology and Science", proofsheets, 1916 (Box 35, Folder 869)
    - Book reviews, 1916 November 6 (Box 35, Folder 870)
    - Letter to the editor of, 1917 January 20 (Box 35, Folder 871)
    - Essay: "The Conceivable Virtue of Patience", printed, 1917 February 22 (Box 35, Folder 872)
    - Book review of Hugh Elliot's Herbert Spencer, 1917 May 10 (Box 35, Folder 873)
    - Essay: Preface to Sumner's Protectionism and Other Essays, TMs, 1917 (Box 35, Folder 874)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1918 January 21 (Box 35, Folder 875)
    - Essay: "The B.A. Degree in America", printed, 1918 February (Box 35, Folder 876)
    - Letter to the editor of the Nation, 1918 February 7 (Box 35, Folder 877)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1918 April 17, August 26 (Box 35, Folder 878-879)
    - Essay: "On Getting the Subject of Military Morale Across to the Officers", 1918 October 11 (Box 36, Folder 880)
    - Lecture: "The Benefits of Government, Law and Order", TMs, 1918 December 4 (Box 36, Folder 881)
    - Lecture: "Law and Order between Nations", TMs, 1918 December (Box 36, Folder 882)
    - Lecture: "The Passing of the Kings", TMs, 1918 December (Box 36, Folder 883)
    - Lecture: "Service and Self-Respect", TMs, 1918 December 18 (Box 36, Folder 884)
    - Lecture: "The Price of Liberty", AMs and TMs, 1918 December 27 (Box 36, Folder 885)
    - Lecture: "The Limits of Liberty", TMs, 1918 December 27 (Box 36, Folder 886)
    - Lecture: "On Sticking by our Allies", TMs, 1918 December 27 (Box 36, Folder 887)
    - Lecture Series I
      - "National Modesty and Fairness", TMs, 1918 December 18 (Box 36, Folder 888)
      - "How American Citizens Govern Themselves", TMs, 1918 December 21 (Box 36, Folder 889)
      - "Where Do We Go from Here?", TMs, 1919 February 13 (Box 36, Folder 890)
    - Lecture Series II
      - "Money and Wages", 1918 December 18 (Box 36, Folder 891)
      - "Thrift and Insurance", 1918 December 23 (Box 36, Folder 892)
      - "The Farmer of Today", TMs, 1918 December 26 (Box 36, Folder 893)
    - Lecture Series III
      - "Real Jobs and How to Pull Them Down," AMs and TMs, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 894)
      - "On Loafing as an Occupation", AMs and TMs, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 895)
      - "The Job that Pays", TMs, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 896)
      - "On Being Fit for One's Job", AMs and TMs, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 897)
      - "On Getting a Better Job", AMs and TMs, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 898)
      - "On the Importance of One's Job", TMs, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 899)
      - "On Pride in Workmanship", TMs, 1919 (Box 36, Folder 900)
      - "Present Opportunities for Getting Jobs", TMs, 1919 February 7 (Box 36, Folder 901)
        See also: box 2, folder 48 See also: box 10, folder 373
    - Lecture: "On the State," TMs, 1918-1919 (Box 36, Folder 902)
    - Essay: "Democracy vs. Autocracy", TMs, 1914-1919 (Box 36, Folder 903)
    - Lecture: "Civil Liberty", AMs and TMs, 1918-1919 (Box 36, Folder 904)
    - Lecture: "The Service of Government", TMs, 1918-1919 (Box 36, Folder 905)
    - Essay: "What the Home-Folks Have Done", Ams and TMs, 1918-1919 (Box 36, Folder 906)
    - Essay: "Graduate Views on Reorganization Problems", printed, 1919 February 14 (Box 37, Folder 906a)
    - Essay: "Some Defects of the Ph.D.", printed, 1919 June 13 (Box 37, Folder 907)
    - Essay: "Law in Evolution", printed, 1919 June (Box 37, Folder 907a)
    - Essay: "Post-War Education", printed, 1919 August 9 (Box 37, Folder 908)
    - Essay: "On Cultivating the Fundamentals", printed, 1919 August 16 (Box 37, Folder 909)
    - Essay: "College Salaries and College Quality", printed, 1919 August 23 (Box 37, Folder 910)
    - Speech to graduating seniors, 1919 (Box 37, Folder 911)
    - Letter to the editor of the Alumni Weekly, TMs, 1919 (Box 37, Folder 912)
    - Essay: "The Menace of Piffle", TMs, 1918-19[?] (Box 37, Folder 912a)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1920 October 28 (Box 37, Folder 913)
    - Essay: "Race Distinction", proofsheets, 1920 (Box 37, Folder 914)
    - Essay: "Race Distinction", printed, 1920 (Box 37, Folder 915)
      See also: box 14, folder 576 See also: box 53, folder 1427
    - Book review of Carveth Read's The Origin of Man and His Superstitions, 1921 April 2 (Box 37, Folder 916)
    - Book review of Paul Vinogradoff's Outlines of Historical Jurisprudence, 1921 April (Box 37, Folder 917)
    - Book review of William McDougall's Is America Safe for Democracy, 1921 July 23 (Box 37, Folder 918)
    - Book review of Lothrop Stoddard's The Revolt Against Civilization, 1922 September 9 (Box 37, Folder 919)
    - Essay: "General Practice", TMs, 1922 November 28 (Box 37, Folder 920)
    - Letters to the editor, 1922, 1944, 1948 (Box 37, Folder 921)
    - Letter to the editor of the News, TMs, 1923 March (Box 37, Folder 922)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, TMs, 1924 October 18 (Box 37, Folder 923)
    - Student notes of Keller's anthropology lectures, 1925 April 20,22,24,27,29, May 1,4,6,8,11,13,15,18,20,22,25,27,29 (Box 37, Folder 924-941)
    - Book review of Heinrich Schneg's German Colonization Past and Future, TMs, 1926 (Box 37, Folder 942)
    - Book review of H. W. Haggard's The Science of Health and Disease, TMs and printed, 1928 June 9 (Box 37, Folder 943)
    - Essay: "On the Conflicts between Scientists and Artists, "TMs, 1929 January 3 (Box 37, Folder 944)
    - Essay: "Marriage and the Family", TMs, 1929 March 14 (Box 37, Folder 945)
    - Essay: "The Ant and the Butterfly", printed, 1929 April 6 (Box 37, Folder 946)
    - Essay: "Discipline and Freedom", printed, 1929 May 8 (Box 37, Folder 947)
    - Essay: "Prerequisite to Prophecy", TMs, 1929 July 21 (Box 37, Folder 948)
    - Essay: "Religion and Science", printed, 1929 August 14 (Box 37, Folder 949)
    - Essay: On Revising His Arguments in Societal Evolution, TMs, 1922-1929 (Box 37, Folder 950)
    - Essay: "War", TMs, 1930 January 3 (Box 37, Folder 951)
    - Essay: "Divorce", TMs, 1930 April 12-13 (Box 37, Folder 952)
    - Essay: "Birth Control", printed, 1930 April 16 (Box 37, Folder 953)
    - Essay: "The Drift to Peace", printed, 1930 May 7 (Box 37, Folder 954)
    - Book review of R. M. MacIver's Society, Its Structure and Changes, TMs, 1931 (Box 37, Folder 955)
    - Essay: "The Discoverer of the Forgotten Man", Printed, 1932 November (Box 37, Folder 956)
    - Essay: "The Poet Knows", AMs, 1933 June 21 (Box 37, Folder 957)
    - Essay: "The Accursed Armchair", TMs, revised in 1935, 1933 (Box 37, Folder 958)
    - Essay: "Is Thrift Overdone? Is Poor Richard Out of Date?", AMs, 1933 July 3 (Box 37, Folder 959)
    - Essay: "Criticism of the New Deal", Ams, 1933 October 6 (Box 37, Folder 960)
    - Essay: "Mussolini: A Realist Who Seems to Know What He Is About", printed, 1935 September 27 (Box 37, Folder 961)
      See also: box 3, folder 92 See also: box 6, folder 209, 212, 215 See also: box 7, folder 228 See also: box 7, folder 234 See also: box 41, folder 1141
    - Essay: "A Message from Professor Keller", Printed, 1935 November (Box 37, Folder 962)
    - Speech: Eulogy on Edwin Cassius Taylor, TMs, 1935 December 18 (Box 37, Folder 963)
    - Book review of Lawrence Henderson's Pareto's General Sociology, printed, 1935 December (Box 37, Folder 964)
    - Essay: "Pareto", AMs, 1935 (Box 37, Folder 965)
    - Book review of William Robson's Civilization and the Growth of Law, 1935 (Box 37, Folder 966)
    - Letter to the editor of The Times, TMs, 1936 April 28, July 28 (Box 37, Folder 967-968)
    - Essay: "Professor Keller Also Will Take a Walk" Herald-Tribune, 1936 August 30 (Box 37, Folder 969)
    - Essay on the 1936 presidential election, TMs, 1936 October 17 (Box 37, Folder 970)
    - Essay: "The 'Communist' Label", 1936 October 20 (Box 37, Folder 971)
    - Letter to the editor of The Sun, 1936 October 23 (Box 37, Folder 972)
    - Essay: "Robot, Newest Phase--Germany's Recurrent Disease Breaks out Afresh", TMs, 1936 October 30 (Box 37, Folder 973)
    - Essay: "Some Reflections of a Cleveland-Wilson Democrat", TMs, 1936 October 30 (Box 37, Folder 974)
    - Essay: "Keller Sees Sumner as Anti-New Dealer" Washington Post, 1936 November 1 (Box 37, Folder 975)
    - Essay: "How Long Can All the People Be Fooled?", TMs, 1936 November 1 (Box 37, Folder 976)
    - Essay: "Educational Planning", printed, 1936 November 21-26 (Box 38, Folder 977)
    - Essay: "An Independent Democrat Takes a Walk", TMs, 1936 (Box 38, Folder 978)
    - Essay: What Would Sumner Have Thought?", TMs, 1936 [?] (Box 38, Folder 979)
    - Essay: "Confidence", AMs, 1936 (Box 38, Folder 980)
    - Essay: "The Era of Bugle-Pounders", TMs, revised July 1946, 1936 (Box 38, Folder 981)
    - Essay: "On the Organization of an Opposition", TMs, 1937 January 19 (Box 38, Folder 982)
    - Essay: Critique of "On the Organization of an Opposition", AMs, 1937 (Box 38, Folder 983)
    - Essay: "Educational 'Planning", printed, 1937 February (Box 38, Folder 984)
    - Letter to the editor of the Herald-Tribune, 1937 April 22 (Box 38, Folder 985)
    - Essay: "Machiavelli and Vibrancy", TMs, 1937 July 19 (Box 38, Folder 986)
    - Letter to the editor, 1937 December 24 (Box 38, Folder 987)
    - Letter to the editor of the Herald-Tribune, 1937 December 28 (Box 38, Folder 988)
    - Essay: "'Applied' Sociology", TMs, 1938 (Box 38, Folder 989)
    - Essay on the study of evolution, AMs, 1939 January 31 (Box 38, Folder 990)
    - Essay: "A Recess of Variation", TMs, post-1933 (Box 38, Folder 991)
    - Essay on the problem of life in society, AMs, post-1933 (Box 38, Folder 992)
    - Essay on militarism, TMs, pre-1939 (Box 38, Folder 993)
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Herald-Tribune, 1930 December 22 (Box 38, Folder 994)
    - Essay: "Sumnerology", TMs, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 995)
    - Essay: "Sumner", TMs, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 996)
    - Essay: "How Sumner Arrived at His Conclusions", TMs, 1940 (Box 38, Folder 997)
    - Letter to the editor of the Herald-Tribune, 1942 June 2 (Box 38, Folder 998)
    - Essay: "Can Science Enter the Societal Range", printed, 1942 June 22 (Box 38, Folder 999)
    - Essay: "One Layman's Rating of the World Poets", TMs, 1942 July 28 (Box 38, Folder 1000)
    - Essay: "Are All Germans Nazis?", TMs, 1942 August 6 (Box 38, Folder 1001)
    - Letter to the editor of the Herald-Tribune, TMs, 1942 November 25 (Box 38, Folder 1002)
    - Essay: "Toward a People's Peace", TMs, 1943 January 5 (Box 38, Folder 1003-1004)
    - Essay: "Message from Professor A. G. Keller", printed, 1943 January (Box 38, Folder 1005)
    - Letter to the editor, TMs, 1943 March 31 (Box 38, Folder 1006)
    - Essay: "Terminology", printed, 1943 April (Box 38, Folder 1007)
    - Letter to the editor, TMs, 1943 June 13,21 (Box 38, Folder 1008-1009)
    - Essay: "The Case for Toughness", TMs, 1943[?] (Box 38, Folder 1010)
    - Essay: "The Tough Teachings of Mars", TMs, post-1942 (Box 38, Folder 1011)
    - Essay: "What the Pinch Reveals", TMs, post-1942 (Box 38, Folder 1012)
    - Essay: "The Preoccupation with 'Face'", printed, 1944 February 19 (Box 38, Folder 1013)
    - Letter to the editor of the Herald-Tribune, TMs, 1944 March 16 (Box 38, Folder 1014)
    - Essay: "The Political Symbol and Some Others", TMs, 1944 April 28 (Box 38, Folder 1015)
    - Essay: "The Transplantation of Democracy", 1944 June 12 (Box 38, Folder 1016)
    - Government Responsibility in Tort--A Proposal Statutory Reform, 1944 August 3 (Box 38, Folder 1017)
    - Essay: "Soundness at Home, or Nowhere", TMs, 1944 August 30 (Box 38, Folder 1018)
    - Letter to the editor of the Register, 1944 October 31 (Box 38, Folder 1019)
    - Essay: "What of 'Loyal Opposition'", TMs, 1944 November 21 (Box 38, Folder 1020)
    - Essay: "On Seeing What Is Before Our Eyes", TMs, 1944 November 22 (Box 38, Folder 1021)
    - Essay: "The Russian Exploit", TMs, 1944 November 28 (Box 38, Folder 1022)
    - Essay: "Commercial Isolationism", AMs and TMs, 1944 December 1 (Box 38, Folder 1023)
    - Essay: "What We Cannot Afford", TMs, 1944 December 1 (Box 38, Folder 1024)
    - Essay: "Where and Whither?", AMs and TMs, 1944 December 2 (Box 38, Folder 1025)
    - Essay: "The Half-Truth and the 'Good Reason'", AMs and TMs, 1944 December 3 (Box 38, Folder 1026)
    - Essay: "A Forgotten Partner", TMs, 1944 December 3 (Box 38, Folder 1027)
    - Essay: "What Is a 'Social Accomplishment'?", TMs, 1944 December 10 (Box 38, Folder 1028)
    - Essay: "War Literature I and II", TMs, 1944 December 12-13 (Box 38, Folder 1029)
    - Essay: "The God-Man", 1944 December 15 (Box 38, Folder 1030)
    - Essay: "From the Sublime to the Earthy", TMs, 1944 December 16 (Box 38, Folder 1031)